Good morning. Today we're going to talk about
早上好  今天我们要讨论
a new balanced search structure,
一种新的平衡搜索结构
so a data structure that maintains a dynamic set
这种数据结构可以维护动态数据集
subject to insertion, deletion,
支持插入 删除
and search called skip lists.
还有搜索  称为跳跃表
So, I'll call this a dynamic search structure
它是个动态搜索结构
because it's a data structure.
因为这个数据结构
It supports search, and it's dynamic, meaning insert and delete.
它支持搜索 而且它是动态的 即支持插入和删除
So, what other dynamic search structures do we know,
好 我们还知道有什么动态搜索结构呢？
just for sake of comparison, and to wake everyone up?
作个对比  唤醒一下大家的记忆
Shout them out, efficient, I should say,
知道的说一下  高效的 我补充一点
also good, logarithmic time per operation.
而且是良好的  每个操作只需对数级的时间
So, this is a really easy question to get us off the ground.
这个问题真的弱爆了
You've seen them all in the last week,
这些结构你们上周都见过了
so it shouldn't be so hard.
这不难吧
Treap, good. On the problems that we saw treaps.
树堆 很好 在习题里我们见过树堆
That's, in some sense,
这可以说是
the simplest dynamic search structure
我们用基本概念构造出来的
you can get from first principles
最简单的动态搜索结构
because all we needed was a bound
因为我们只是想给
on a randomly constructed binary search tree.
随机化二叉搜索树找一个限界
And then treaps did well.
而且树堆运作得不错
So, that was sort of the first one you saw depending on
大概 你们最先接触到是它
when you did your problem set. What else?
当然 这取决于你做习题的时间  还有什么
Charles?
查哥！
[Charles]Red black trees,
红黑树
[Erik]Red black trees, it's a good answer.
红黑树  答得好
So, that was exactly one week ago. I hope you still remember it.
这个刚好是一周前的内容  我希望大家还记得
They have guaranteed log n performance.
红黑树的性能为 O(log n)
So, this was an expected bound.
树堆是有一个期望限界
This was a worst-case order log n per operation,
而红黑树则是最坏情况复杂度为O(log n)
insert, delete, and search.
对插入 删除 搜索都成立
And, there was one more
还有一个
for those who want to recitation on Friday: B trees, good.
周五的习题课上提到的  B树 很好
And, by B trees, I also include two-three trees,
提到B树 我还想提一下 2-3-树
two-three-four trees, and all those guys.
2-3-4-树 等等
So, if B is a constant,
也就是说 无论B是一个常数
or if you want your B trees knows a little bit cleverly,
还是你B树选得更为灵活
that these have guaranteed order log n performance,
它们都保证有 O(log n) 的性能
so, worst case, order log n.
也就是说 它的最坏情况也是O(log n）
So, you should know this.
这是大家应该了解的
These are all balanced search structures.
这些都是平衡搜索结构
They are dynamic. They support insertions and deletions.
它们是动态的 支持插入和删除
They support searches, finding a given key.
它们支持特定键值的搜索
And if you don't find the key, you find its predecessor
如果你要找的不是键值本身
and successor pretty easily in all of these structures.
你也能很容易找到它前前后后的元素
If you want to augment some data structure,
假如说 我们想扩张某个数据结构
you should think about which one of these is easiest to augment
我们首先思考哪种结构是最容易扩张的
as in Monday's lecture.
这是周一课上的内容
So, the question I want to pose to you is supposed
现在问题是
I gave you all a laptop right now, which would be great.
假如我现在送你一台本本  爽吧
Then I asked you,
然后我说
in order to keep this laptop you have to implement
送给你的条件是
one of these data structures, let's say, within this class hour.
你要实现这里其中一种结构  就在这节课上完成
Do you think you could do it?
你觉得你能做到吗？
How many people think you could do it?
有多少人觉得自己可以做到？
A couple people, a few people, OK, all front row people, good.
有一些人觉得可以 都是我们的前排部队 很好
I could probably do it. My preference would be B trees.
我应该可以做到 我偏向于实现B树
They're sort of the simplest in my mind.
我觉得它是最简单的了
This is without using the textbook.
当然是不让翻书的哈
This would be a closed book exam.
这是闭卷考试
I don't have enough laptops to do it, unfortunately.
很不幸的是 我没有那么多台本本来考验你们
So, B trees are pretty reasonable.
总之实现B树是比较合理的
Deletion, you have to remember
做删除时  你要记得
stealing from a sibling and whatnot.
从邻近结点处转移元素 等等
So, deletions are a bit tricky.
删除是有技巧的
Red black trees, I can never remember it.
红黑树我怎么也记不住
I'd have to look it up, or re-derive the three cases.
我总要查查书 或者再推导一遍那三种情况
treaps are a bit fancy.
树堆的实现更花哨一点
So, that would take a little while
所以 要花点时间
to remember exactly how those work.
才能记住怎么弄
You'd have to solve your problem set again,
你可能得再做一次习题集的题
if you don't have it memorized.
如果你不记得的话
Skip lists, on the other hand,
但是 跳跃表
are a data structure you will never forget,
却是一种你一定忘不了的数据结构
and something you can implement within an hour, no problem.
你可以在一个小时内实现它 没有问题
I've made this claim a couple times before,
这话我以前讲过很多遍
and I always felt bad because I had never actually done it.
但是我从未做到过 搞得我很有挫败感
So, this morning, I implemented skip lists,
所以今天早上 我把跳跃表做出来了
and it took me ten minutes to implement a linked list,
我花了10分钟实现了链表
and 30 minutes to implement skip lists.
然后花30分钟实现了跳跃表
And another 30 minutes debugging them. There you go.
最后花了30分钟调试  鉴定完毕
It can be done. Skip lists are really simple.
这是可以做到的 跳跃表真的很简单
And, at no point writing the code did I have to think,
而且在写代码的时候  我都不需要深入思考
whereas every other structure I would have to think.
但写其他结构时 我总是要想想
There was one moment when I thought, ah, how do I flip a coin?
有些时候我总要停下来 想想我该怎么抛硬币呢
That was the entire amount of thinking.
然后脑袋就堵塞了
So, skip lists are a randomized structure.
所以 跳跃表是一个随机化的结构
Let's add in another adjective here,
我们在这里多加点形容词
and let's also add in simple.
加个“简单”吧
So, we have a simple, efficient, dynamic,
我们得到的是一个简单的、高效的、动态的
randomized search structure: all those things together.
随机化搜索结构 集合了各种优点
So, it's sort of like treaps
它有点像树堆
and that the bound is only a randomized bound.
它的界是随机化的
But today, we're going to see
但是今天我们会看到
a much stronger bound than an expectation bound.
一个比期望界限还要强得多的界
So, in particular,
特别地
skip lists will run in order log n expected time.
跳跃表期望的运行时间为 O(log n)
So, the running time for each operation
所以 每一个操作的运行时间的
will be order log n in expectation.
期望均为 O(log n)
But, we're going to prove a much stronger result
但我们要证明一个更强大的结果
that their order log n, with high probability.
不单是O(log n)  而且发生概率很高
So, this is a very strong claim. And it means that
这种说法其实很强大  它意味着
the running time of each operation,
每次操作的运行时间
the running time of every operation,
每一步操作的运行时间
is order log n almost always in a certain sense.
几乎总是 O(log n)
Why don't I foreshadow that?
更进一步地 我剧透一下
So, it's something like, the probability that it's order log n
出现O(log n) 时间的概率是 比如说
is at least one minus one over some polynomial, and n.
至少是 1 减去某个 n 的多项式的倒数
And, you get to set the polynomial however large you like.
而且 我们可以令多项式充分大
So, what this basically means is that almost all the time,
这也就是说 几乎所有情况下
you take your skip lists,
操作跳跃表
you do a polynomial number of operations on it,
假设操作次数是多项式级的
because presumably you are running a polynomial time algorithm
假设我们在运行一个时间是多项式级的算法
that using this data structure.
它用到了这个数据结构
Do polynomial numbers of inserts, delete searches,
那么做多项式次的插入 删除或搜索操作
every single one of them
每一个操作的时间
will take order log n time, almost guaranteed.
几乎可以保证均为 O(log n)
So this is a really strong bound on the tail of the distribution.
这给概率分布的尾部加了一个很强的界
The mean is order log n. That's not so exciting.
平均运行时间是 O(log n)  貌似这没什么大不了
But, in fact,
而实际上
almost all of the weight of this probability distribution
几乎所有的概率分布的权值
is right around the log n, just tiny little epsilons,
都落在log n的邻域内 只有非常小量的
very tiny probabilities you could be bigger than log n.
在极小概率情况下会超过 log n
So that's where we are going.
我们的目的是证明这个
This is a data structure by Pugh in 1989.
这是1989年由 Pugh 提出的数据结构
This is the most recent.
这个是最新的成果
Actually, no, sorry, treaps are more recent.
噢 抱歉 树堆才是最新的结果
They were like '93 or so,
它大概是93年左右做出来的
but a fairly recent data structure
不过跳跃表还是一个很新的数据结构
for just insert, delete, search.
实现了插入 删除和搜索功能
And, it's very simple. You can derive it
而且它很简单 你甚至能把它推导出来
if you don't know anything about data structures,
即使你对数据结构一无所知
well, almost nothing.
几乎不需要准备知识
Now, analyzing that the performance is log n,
分析它的性能的界是 O(log n)
that, of course, takes our sophistication.
才是我们证明的关键
But the data structure itself is very simple.
这种数据结构本身是简单的
We're going to start from scratch.
我们现在从零开始
Suppose you don't know what a red black tree is.
假设我们不知道什么是红黑树
You don't know what a B tree is.
不知道什么是B树
Suppose you don't even know what a tree is.
假设我们连树是什么都不知道
What is the simplest data structure
那么 存储一堆动态数据的
for storing a bunch of items for storing a dynamic set?
最简单的数据结构是什么？
A list, good, a linked list.
表 很好 特别地 是一个链表
Now, suppose that it's a sorted linked list.
现在假设它是一个排好序的链表
So, I'm going to be a little bit fancier there.
这里我们用一点高级点的东西哈
So, if you have a linked list of items, here it is,
现在 我们有一个链表
maybe we'll make it doubly linked just for kicks,
为了好玩 定义它为一个双向链表吧
how long does it take to search in a sorted linked list?
搜索一个排好序的链表需要多长时间
Log n is one answer. n is the other answer.
我听到一个答案是 O(log n) 还有 O(n)
Which one is right? n is the right answer.
哪个是对的？  O(n)是对的
So, even though it's sorted, we can't do binary search
即便链表已经排好序了 我们也没法做二分查找
because we don't have random-access into a linked list.
因为我们不能随机访问链表元素
So, suppose I'm only given a pointer to the head.
假设我只给出一个指向表头的指针
Otherwise, I'm assuming it's an array.
反过来 假设这是一个数组的话
So, in a sorted array you can search in log n.
在排序数组里 搜索时间就可以是O(log n)
Sorted linked list: you've still
对于排序链表
got to scan through the darn thing.
我们就得遍历整个破玩意儿
So, theta n, worst case search.
所以 最坏情况时间为 Θ(n)
Not so good, but if we just try to improve it a little bit,
这个不是很好 但如果我们逐步改进它
we will discover skip lists automatically.
我们就能自然而然地推出跳跃表
So, this is our starting point: sorted linked lists, theta n time.
这就是我们的起点 排序链表 Θ(n) 的时间
And, I'm not going to think too much
现在我暂不考虑插入和删除
Let's just get search better, and then we'll worry about updates.
我们先来改进搜索 然后再来操心结构的更新
Updates are where randomization will come in.
因为更新的时候才会出现随机化
Search: pretty easy idea.
搜索的思想很简单的
So, how can we make a linked list better?
那么 我们如何去改进链表？
Suppose all we know about our linked lists.
假设我们已知的链表的所有性质
What can I do to make it faster?
怎么样才能让它更快
This is where you need a little bit
这时 我们就需要
of innovation, some creativity.
一点创新 一点创造力
More links: that's a good idea. So, I could try to
加入更多的链接？ 这个想法不错
maybe add pointers to go a couple steps ahead.
比如说 我再加几个指向后面元素的指针
If I had log n pointers, I could do all powers of two ahead.
只要加log n个指针 我就可以实现2的幂次的访问
That's a pretty good search structure. Some people use that;
这是一个很好的搜索结构 有些人现在就在用
like, some peer-to-peer networks use that idea.
比如说某些点对点网络就是这个原理
But that's a little too fancy for me.
不过就这个东西太花哨了
[Student]Inaudible.
[学生]。。。
Ah, good. You could try to build a tree on this linear structure.
嗯 好 我们可以从这个线性结构里构造出一棵树
That's essentially where we're going.
我们其实正要这么做
So, you could try to put pointers to,
我们可以把根节点的下一位
like, the middle of the list from the roots.
指向链表的中位元素
So, you search between either here.
然后下一步从这里开始搜索  又或者
You point to the median, so you can compare against the median,
首先我们指向中位 然后我们再比较大小
and know whether you should go in the first half or the second half
决定是搜索前半部分 还是后半
that's definitely on the right track,
方向是正确的
also a bit too sophisticated.
但是这还是太复杂了
Another list: yes. Yes, good.
使用另一个链表 对 对 非常好
So, we are going to use two lists.
我们准备使用两个链表
That's sort of the next simplest thing you could do.
这也许是我们能够做到的第二容易的事
OK, and as you suggested,
好 就像你说的
we could maybe have pointers between them.
我们用指针连接两个链表
So, maybe we have some elements down here,
然后 有些元素在下面
some of the elements up here.
有些元素在上面
We want to have pointers between the lists.
链表之间用指针相连
OK, it gets a little bit crazy in how exactly you might do that.
这个做法看起来有点疯狂
But somehow, this feels good.
不过现在还好
So this is one linked list: L_1.
现在 这是链表L1
This is another linked list: L_2.
这是另一个链表L2
And, to give you some inspiration,
现在 为了给大家一点直观的启示
I want to give you, so let's play a game.
我先讲一个 额 我们来玩一个游戏
The game is, what is this sequence?
游戏是 数列猜猜猜
So, the sequence is 14...
这个数列是 14。。。
If you know the answer, shout it out.
如果你知道答案 那就吼出来
Anyone yet? OK, it's tricky.
有人知道么 哈 这个问题有点奇葩
It's a bit of a small class,
我们这是个小班
so I hope someone knows the answer.
我希望有人知道答案
How many TA's know the answer?
有多少助教知道答案
Just a couple, OK, if you're looking at the slides,
只有几个 没关系 如果你们看过幻灯片
probably you know the answer.
可能会知道答案
That's cheating. OK, I'll give you a hint.
那是作弊哦亲 我给一点提示
It is not a mathematical sequence.
这不是一个数学上的数列
This is a real-life sequence. Yeah?
这是一个现实生活中的数列 请说
Yeah, and what city? New York, yeah, this is the 7th Ave line.
对 什么城市的 纽约 正确 这是第七大道线
This is my favorite subway line in New York.
我最喜欢的纽约地铁线
But, what's a cool feature of the New York City subway?
纽约地铁有什么很酷的性质呢
OK, it's a skip list. Good answer.
它是一个跳跃表 答得好
[LAUGHTER]
[笑声]
Indeed it is. Skip lists are so practical.
它确实是一个跳跃表 跳跃表是非常实用的
They've been implemented in the subway system. How cool is that?
地铁线路就实现了跳跃表 酷爆了
OK, Boston subway is pretty cool because it's the oldest subway
这样说吧 波士顿的地铁很棒 因为它是全美最老的地铁
definitely in the United States, maybe in the world.
可能还是全球最老的
New York is close,
纽约地铁的历史同样悠久
and it has other nice features like it's open 24 hours.
更不错的是 它还是24小时运营的
That's a definite plus,
这也是它的优势之一
but it also has this feature of express lines.
但它有一个很重要的特点就是有快线
So, it's a bit of an abstraction,
这样讲可能有点抽象
but the 7th Ave line has essentially two kinds of cars.
第七大道线有两种列车
These are street numbers by the way.
顺便讲一句这是街道编号
This is, Penn Station, Times Square, and so on.
这是宾州广场站 时代广场站 等等
So, there are essentially two lines.
它实际上有两条线
There's the express line
快线在14 34 42 72和96街设有车站
And then, there's the local line which stops at every stop.
慢线则站站停车
And, they accomplish this with four sets of tracks.
这是通过四条轨道实现的
So, I mean, the express lines have their own dedicated track.
也就是说 快车在单独的轨道上运行
If you want to go to stop 59 from, let's say, Penn Station,
比如说 现在我们从宾州广场站 想去往59街
well, let's say from lower west side,
不 还是从城西出发吧
you get on the express line.
首先我们上快线
You jump to 42 pretty quickly,
很快地我们来到42街
and then you switch over to the local line,
然后换乘慢车
and go on to 59 or wherever I said I was going.
再到59街或者随便什么站
OK, so this is express and local lines,
这就是快线和慢线
and we can represent that with a couple of lists.
我们可以用一些链表来表示它们
We have one list,
首先我们有一层链表
sure, we have one list on the bottom,
首先我们有一层底链表
so leave some space up here.
上面留点地方
This is the local line, L_2,
这是慢线L2
34, 42, 50, 59, 66, 72, 79, and so on.
34 42 50 59 66 72 79等等
And then we had the express line on top,
上面是快线
which only stops at 14, 34, 42, 72, and so on.
只停14 34 42 72等等
I'm not going to redraw the whole list. You get the idea.
我就不把整个链表画出来了 你懂的
And so, what we're going to do is put links between
然后我们把快线和慢线...
in the local and express lines, wherever they happen to meet.
它们都停的车站 给链接起来
And, that's our two linked list structure.
这就是我们得到的双链表结构
So, that's what I actually meant
我就是这个意思
what I was trying to draw some picture.
就是这里画的这个图
Now, this has a property that in one list,
注意 这里有一个性质
the bottom list, every element occurs.
这一个底链表  它包含了所有元素
And the top list just copies some of those elements.
而在顶链表中只包含了其中几个元素
And we're going to preserve that property.
我们将会保持这个性质
So, L_2 stores all the elements,
即L2存储全部元素
and L_1 stores some subset.
L1只存某些子集
And, it's still open which ones we should store.
至于存的是哪些元素  现在还是未定
That's the one thing we need to think about.
这也是我们需要考虑的一点
But, our inspiration is from the New York subway system.
我们的灵感是来自纽约地铁系统
OK, there, that the idea.
好的 这是我们的出发点
Of course, we're also going to use more than two lists.
当然 我们会用到不止两个链表
OK, we also have links.
对了 我们还有链接
Let's say it links between equal keys in L_1 and L_2.
L1和L2中 键值相同的元素之间有链接
Good. So, just for the sake of completeness,
好的  为了课程的完整性
and because we will need this later, let's talk about searches
因为等会才会用到这个 我们首先讨论搜索
before we worry about how these lists are actually constructed.
稍候再考虑链表如何构造
Of course, if I wanted that board.
换个黑板先
So, if you want to search for an element, x, what do you do?
比如说 我们要查找一个元素x 应该怎么做
Well, this is the taking the subway algorithm.
这是坐地铁算法哈
And, suppose you always start
假设我们总是在
in the upper left corner of the subway system,
左上角入站
if you're always in the lower west side, 14th St,
也就是在城西的14街
and I don't know exactly where that is, but more or less,
我不知道准确的方位在哪
somewhere down at the bottom of Manhattan.
总之是在曼哈顿地下某处
And, you want to go to a particular station like 59.
假设我们要去往某个特定的车站 比如59街
Well, you'd stay on the express line as long as you can
那我们在快线上 肯定是能坐多远坐多远
because it happens that we started on the express line.
因为我们一开始就在快线上
And then, you go down.
然后我们往下走
And then you take the local line the rest of the way.
坐慢车到59街
That's clearly the right thing to do
这当然是正确的做法
if you always start in the top left corner.
假设我们从左上角开始的话
So, I'm going to write that down in some kind of an algorithm
现在我把步骤总结成算法
because we will be generalizing it.
因为我们要推广它
It's pretty obvious at this point. It will remain obvious.
目前的情况是很显然的 往后的情形也很简单
So, I want to walk right in the top list
现在我要在顶链表上一直往右跑
until that would go too far.
直到跑过头
So, you imagine giving someone directions
想像一下你在告诉一个
on the subway system they've never been on.
从未坐过地铁的人如何搭乘地铁
So, you say, OK, you start at 14th. Take the express line,
你会说 嗯 从14街入站 坐快线
and when you get to 72nd, you've gone too far.
如果坐到了72街站 你就坐过头了
Go back one, and then go down to the local line.
往回坐一个站 然后换乘慢线
It's really annoying directions.
但问路的人就被气死了
But this is what an algorithm has to do
不过算法必须要这样
because it's never taken the subway before.
因为计算机从未坐过地铁
So, it's going to check, so let's do it here.
现在我们跟着这个图过一遍 写在这儿吧
So, suppose I'm aiming for 59.
假设我要去59街
So, I started 14, say the first thing I do is go to 34.
我从14街入站 首先我坐到34街
Then from there, I go to 42.
然后坐到42街
Still good because 59 is bigger than 42.
还好 因为59大于42
I go right again. I say, oops, 72 is too big. That was too far.
我再坐一个站 然后 哦噢 72太大了 我坐过站了
So, I go back to where it just was.
然后我往回坐一个站
Then I go down and then I keep going right
然后我跑下来继续往右跑
until I find the element that I want,
直到我找到想找的元素
or discover that it's not in the bottom list
或者发现它不在底链表中
because bottom list has everyone.
因为底链表中已经包括了所有元素
So, that's the algorithm.
这就是整个算法
Stop when going right would go too far,
一直往右跑直到跑过头
and you discover that with a comparison.
判断有没有跑过头 只须比较一下大小就行了
Then you walk down to L_2.
然后下到L2
And then you walk right in L_2 until you find x,
继续在L2上往右跑直到找到x
or you find something greater than x,
或者找到一个元素大于x
in which case x is definitely not on your list.
那就表明x不在表中
And you found the predecessor and successor,
不过我们能找出它的前后的元素
which may be your goal.
这也可能是我们需要的
If you didn't find where x was,
如果我们找不到x
you should find where it would go if it were there,
我们可以找出x应该处在的位置
because then maybe you could insert there.
因为插入的时候应该就摆在那儿
We're going to use this algorithm in insertion.
我们在插入的时候就会用到这个算法
OK, but that search: pretty easy at this point.
先讲这么多 总之搜索是很简单的
Now, what we haven't discussed is
现在我们还没讨论
how fast the search algorithm is,
搜索能有多快
and it depends, of course,
当然这取决于
which elements we're going to store in L_1,
我们把什么元素存在L1里
which subset of elements should go in L_1.
L1的元素子集包含了什么
Now, in the subway system,
在地铁系统里
you probably put all the popular stations in L_1.
我们把人流量最大的车站放在L1中
But here, we want worst-case performance.
但在这里 我们是要保证最坏情况性能
So, we don't have some probability distribution on the nodes.
而这些结点也不存在什么概率分布
We just like every node to be accessed
我们希望访问每个结点的速度
sort of as quickly as possible, uniformly.
都能尽可能地快
So, we want to minimize the maximum time over all queries.
也就是 我们希望把最大的查询时间降到最小
So, any ideas what we should do with L_1?
那L1应该怎么设计呢
Should I put all the nodes of L_1 in the beginning?
是不是把所有的结点都放进L1呢？
OK, it's a strict subset.
我们要的是一个真子集吧
Suppose I told you what the size of L_1 was.
假设L1的大小已知
I can tell you, I could afford to build this many express stops.
现在告诉你 我可以出资建造多少个快线车站
How should you distribute them among the elements of L_2?
那么应该如何在L2中加设车站呢？
Uniformly, good. So, what nodes, sorry, what keys,
均匀设站 很好 那么 什么结点 额..什么键值
let's say, go in L_1?
要放进L1呢
Well, definitely the best thing to do is
最佳的选择当然是
to spread them out uniformly,
把它们均匀分布
OK, which is definitely not what the 7th Ave line looks like.
当然这跟第七大道线的情况大不一样
But, let's imagine that we could reengineer everything.
想像我们现在重新设计这一切吧
So, we're going to try to
现在我们想
space these things out a little bit more.
把快线车站分得再开一点
So, 34 and 42nd are way too close.
比如说 34街站和42街站离得太近了
We'll take a few more stops.
我们把它们挪开一点
And, now we can start to analyze things.
现在我们开始分析
OK, as a function of the length of L_1.
用一个关于L1长度的函数
So, the cost of a search is now roughly,
那么搜索的代价大约为——
so, I want a function of the length of L_1,
我们的函数 和L1长度有关
and the length of L_2, which is all the elements, n.
也和L2的长度有关 即元素的个数n
What is the cost of the search
如果我把L1均匀分布
if I spread out all the elements in L_1 uniformly? Yeah?
搜索的代价是多少？
[Student]Inaudible.
[学生]。。。
[Professor]Right, the total number of elements in the top lists,
[教授]对 顶链表的元素个数
plus the division between the bottom and the top.
加上底链表的一节的长度
So, I'll write the length of L_1
也就是
plus the length of L_2 divided by the length of L_1.
|L1|+|L2|/|L1|
OK, this is roughly, I mean,
这是一个粗略的估计
there's maybe a plus one or so here
这儿可能要再加1 什么的
because in the worst case, I have to search through all of L_1
因为 最坏情况下我要遍历整个L1
because the station I could be looking for could be the max.
因为我可能要坐到终点站
OK, and maybe I'm not lucky,
更倒霉的是
and the max is not on the express line.
终点站不在快线上
So then, I have to go down to the local line.
然后我下来换乘慢车
And how many stops will I have to go on the local line?
在慢车上我还要坐多少站？
Well, L_1 just evenly partitions L_2.
因为L1在L2中均匀分布
So this is the number of consecutive stations
所以这是相邻快线车站之间的慢线车站数
So, I take the express, possibly this long,
因此我乘快线 大概这么长
but I take the local possibly this long. So this is in L1
然后换乘慢车 大概这么长  这是在L1中的时间
And, this is an L_2. And there is, plus, a constant,
这是在L2中的时间 这里加个常数
for example, go walking down.
考虑到换乘也需要时间
But that's basically the number of nodes that I visit.
但这大概就是我一共访问到的结点数
So, I'd like to minimize this function.
然后我取它的最小值
Now, L_2, I'm going to call that n
现在我把|L2|换成n
because that's the total number of elements.
因为它等于元素的个数
L_1, I can choose to be whatever I want.
L1是任意选择的
So, let's go over here.
好的 我们换张板子
So, I want to minimize L_1 plus n over L_1.
现在我要取|L1|+n/|L1|的最小值
And I get to choose L_1.
也就是求此时的|L1|
Now, I could differentiate this, set it to zero, and go crazy.
我可以对它求导 令导数为0  傻瓜式推导
Or, I could realize that, I mean, that's not hard.
又或者直接看出 额 虽然并不是很复杂
But, that's a little bit too fancy for me.
不过这种程度也求导 太夸张了
So, I could say, well, this is clearly best when L_1 is small.
首先这项要求|L1|小一点
And this is clearly best when L_1 is large.
这项则要求|L1|大一点
So, there's a trade-off there.
这是一个权衡的因素
And, the trade-off will be roughly minimized up
所以整个东西大概就
to constant factors when these two terms are equal.
在两项相等的时候达到最小值
That's when I have pretty good balance
也就是在两项之间
between the two ends of the trade-off.
刚好达到的平衡的时候
So, this is up to constant factors.
这跟常数n有关
I can let L_1 equal n over L_1, OK,
我令|L1|等于n/|L1|
because at most I'm losing a factor of two there
因为当这两项相等时  上面这条式
when they happen to be equal.
至多等于两倍的|L1|
So now, I just solve this. This is really easy.
现在我来解这个 这个好简单
This is (L_1)^2 equals n.
先推出 |L1|^2=n
So, L_1 is the square root of n.
即|L1|等于n的平方根
OK, so the cost that I'm getting over here,
好的 那么这边的代价算出来
L_1 plus L_2 over L_1 is the square root of n plus n over root n,
就是√n + n /√n
which is, again, root n.
后项也就是√n
So, I get two root n. So, search cost,
然后得到2√n  所以搜索代价是
and I'm caring about the constant here,
注意 我关心这个常数系数
because it will matter in a moment.
因为一会就要用到
Two square root of n:
搜索代价是2√n
I'm not caring about the additive constant,
后面加的常数无关紧要
but the multiplicative constant I care about.
我只关心和n有关的系数
OK, that seems good.
这看上去不错
We started with a linked list that searched in n time,
我们从一个搜索时间 Θ(n) 的链表出发
theta n time per operation.
每个操作 Θ(n) 的时间
Now we have two linked lists, search in theta root n time.
现在我们做成两个链表 搜索时间 Θ(√n)
It seems pretty good. This is what the structure looks like.
这看上去很好 整个结构就是这样的
We have root n guys here. This is in the local line.
我们这有个√n  这是慢线上的一段路
And, we have one express stop which represents that.
这整段对应一个快线车站
But we have another root n values in the local line.
在慢线上又有一段√n的路程
And we have one express stop that represents that.
对应一个快线车站
And these two are linked, and so on.
它们俩是链接的 如此类推
Well, I should put some dot, dot, dots in there.
我在这加些点哈
OK, so each of these chunks has length root n,
好 每个慢线路段的长度是√n
and the number of representatives up here is square root of n.
上面对应的车站个数是√n
The number of express stops is square root of n.
快线车站的个数是√n
So clearly, things are balanced now.
现在整套东西很均衡
I search for, at most, square root of n up here.
在这儿我至多要找过√n个元素
Then I search in one of these lists for,
然后在这样的一段里
at most, square root of n.
至多找过√n个元素
So, every search takes, at most, two root n.
所以每次搜索至多花费2√n的时间
Cool, what should we do next?
很酷吧 接着我们还能做什么
So, again, ignore insertions and deletions.
我们继续无视插入和删除
I want to make searches faster
我还想让搜索再快一点
because square root of n is not so hot as we know.
因为√n还不够过瘾
Sorry?
请说？
More lines. Let's add a super express line,
更多的快线 我们在这加条特快
or another linked list.
也就是另一个链表
OK, this was two. Why not do three?
好 现在有两条 为什么不开三条呢
So, we started with a sorted linked list.
我们从一个排序链表出发
Then we went to two.
然后做成两个链表
This gave us two square root of n.
它们带来了2√n的搜索时间
Now, I want three sorted linked lists. I didn't pluralize here.
现在我准备搞三个排序链表 这里加个s哈
Any guesses what the running time might be?
谁来猜猜运行时间是什么
This is just guesswork. Don't think.
纯猜测 不用仔细想
From two square root of n, you would go to, sorry?
从2√n出发 你能猜到多少？ 嗯嗯？
[Student]Inaudible.
[学生]。。。
[Professor]Two square root of two, fourth root of n?
[教授]2√2*4√n
That's on the right track.
方向对了
Both the constant and the root change, but not quite so fancily.
常数和根式都变了 但没那么复杂
Three times the cubed root: good.
3³√n 很好
Intuition is very helpful here.
这里直觉很重要
It doesn't matter what the right answer is.
对不对并不要紧
Use your intuition.
重要的是运用你的直觉
You can prove that. It's not so hard.
这是可以证明的 证明并不困难
You now have three lists,
现在我们有三个表
and what you want to balance are at the length of the top list,
我们要做的是平衡顶链表的长度
the ratio between the top two lists,
和上两个链表的长度比
and the ratio between the bottom two lists.
以及下两个链表的长度比
So, you want these three to multiply out to n,
然后我们令三项相乘为n
because the top times the ratio times the ratio...
因为顶链表长*上长度比*下长度比
that has to equal n.
=底元素数n
And, so that's where you get the cubed root of n.
³√n就是这样来的
Each of these should be equal.
三项应该相等
So, you set them because the cost
然后因为总代价
is the sum of those three things.
等于三项相加
So, you set each of them to cubed root of n,
然后令三项均为³√n
and there are three of them.
然后有三个 就是3³√n
OK, check it at home if you want to be more sure.
好 如果你们想搞明白的话回去再想一下
Obviously, we want a few more.
显然 我们想要多加几条线
So, let's think about k sorted lists.
现在考虑k个排序链表
k sorted lists will be k times the k'th root of n.
k个链表的效率是 k·k√n
You probably guessed that by now.
现在能猜出来了吧
So, what should we set k to?
我们应该令k等于什么
I don't want the exact minimum.
我不需要一个确切的最小值
What's a good value for k?
什么才是一个好的k值？
Should I set it to n? n's kind of nice,
我能让它等于n吗 n还不太糟
because the n'th root of n is just one.
因为n的n次方根趋近于1
Now that's n. So, this is why I cared about the lead constant
所以结果为n  这就是我关注常系数的原因
because it's going to grow as I add more lists.
因为我多加几个表的时候它会增长
What's the biggest reasonable value of k that I could use?
k值到最大多少才合理？
Log n, because I have a k out there.
log n 因为外面有个k
I certainly don't want to use more than log n.
我当然不想让它大于 log n
So, log n times the log n'th root,
所以效率为 log n 乘以 n的log n次方根
and this is a little hard to draw of n.
有点难写哈
Now, what is the log n'th root of n?
n的log n次方根 等于多少
That's what you're all thinking about.
大家都在想这个吧
What is the log n'th root of n minus two?
n的log n次方根 减2 等于多少
It's one of these good questions whose answer is?
这是我的经典问题哦亲 答案是
Oh man. Remember the definition of root?
噢不会吧 记得根式的定义么
OK, the root is n to the one over log n.
这根式就等于n的 1/log n 次幂
OK, good, remember the definition of having a power, A to the B?
那么 记得A的B次幂的定义么
It was like two to the power, B log A?
是不是长得有点像 2^(B * log A)
Does that sound familiar?
有没有很眼熟的感觉
So, this is two to the log n over log n,
所以它等于 2^(log n / log n)
which is, I hope you can get it at this point, two.
你们都懂的 它等于2
Wow, so the log n'th root of n minus two is zero:
哇噢 所以 n的log n次方根 减2  等于0
my favorite answer.
我最喜欢的答案
OK, this is two. So this whole thing is two log n: pretty nifty.
所以这个等于2 整个式子就等于 2 log n 很帅吧
So, you could be a little fancier and tweak this a little bit,
当然你可以用更高级的技巧 把这个化得更好看一点
but two log n is plenty good for me.
不过我觉得 2 log n 已经足够好了
We clearly don't want to use any more lists,
我们显然不需要更多的表
but log n lists sounds pretty good.
log n 个表刚刚好
I get, now, logarithmic search time. Let's check.
我们现在有对数级的搜索时间了 实验下吧
I mean, we sort of did this all intuitively.
我们前面的结果都是从直观导出来的
Let's draw what the list looks like. But, it will work.
先把表画下来 不过它真的有效
So, I'm going to redraw this example
我先把这个例子重画一遍吧
because you have to, also.
因为你们也要重新画
So, let's redesign that New York City subway system.
现在我们重新设计纽约地铁系统
And, I want you to leave three blank lines up here.
请大家在上面留出三个空行
So, you should have this memorized by now. But I don't.
大家现在都记得了吧 我就记不住
So, we are not allowed to change the local line,
慢线是不变的
though it would be nice, add a few more stops there.
虽然变一下也不会怀孕 多画几个站吧
OK, we can stop at 79th Street. That's enough.
就画到79街 这足够了
So now, we have log n lists.
我们有 log n 个表
And here, log n is about four.
这里 log n 等于4
So, I want to make a bunch of lists here.
这里一会儿还要画一堆表
In particular, 14 will appear on all of them.
特别地 14街出现在每个表中
So, why don't I draw those in?
先画上吧
And, the question is, which elements go in here?
现在问题是 哪些元素会出现在这里
So, I have log n lists. And, my goal is
我们有 log n 个表
to balance the number of items up here,
我的目的是平衡这儿的元素个数
and the ratio between these two lists
以及这两个表的个数比
I want all these things to be balanced.
我想要它们都调平衡
There are log n of them.
我们有 log n 个表
So, the product of all those ratios better be n,
所以各项比值的乘积等于n
the number of elements down here.
即底链表元素的个数
So, the product of all these ratios is n.
各项比值的乘积为n
And there's log n of them; how big is each ratio?
有 log n 个项 每个比值为多少？
So, I'll call the ratio r. The ratio's r.
设这个比值为r
I should have r to the power of log n equals n.
那么有 r^(log n) = n
What's r? What's r minus two?
r等于多少？   r - 2 等于多少？
Zero. OK, this should be two to the power of log n.
0 所以它等于 2^(log n)
So, if the ratio between the number of elements here and here
所以头两个表的个数比是2
is two all the way down,
下面也全是2
then I will have an elements at the bottom, which is what I want.
比值全部相乘就得到底链表的元素个数 即为所求
So, in other words, I want half the elements here,
换句话说  我在这里要放一半的元素
a quarter of the elements here,
这里要放1/4的元素
an eighth of the elements here, and so on.
这里要放1/8的元素 以此类推
So, I'm going to take half of the elements evenly spaced out:
现在我把一半的元素均匀分布
34th, 50th, 66th, 79th, and so on.
34 50 66 79 以此类推
So, this is our new semi-express line: not terribly fast,
这里我们得到了半快线 它不是很快
but you save a factor of two for going up there.
但节约了一半的访问量
And, when you're done, you go down,
在半快线上走到以后 就往下走
and you walk, at most, one step.
你最多也只需要多走一步
And you find what you're looking for.
然后就能找到你要找的元素
OK, and then we do the same thing over and over and over
然后再重复上面的步骤
until we run out of elements. I can't read my own writing.
直到把元素都写完  我都看不清我在写什么了
It's 79th. OK, if I had a bigger example,
这是79 如果我举一个复杂点的例子
I would be more levels,
上面还会多几层
but this is just barely enough.
不过现在也够了
Let's say two elements is where I stop.
我们说最终得到一个表只含两个元素
So, this looks good.
这看起来不错
Does this look like a structure
大家觉不觉得它
you've seen before, at all, vaguely? Yes?
似乎很像我们某个见过的结构呢？  请说？
A tree: yes. It looks a lot like a binary tree.
树 正确 它看起来很像一棵二叉树
I'll just leave it at that. In your problem set,
关于这点我就提一提 大家在做习题集的时候
you'll understand why skip lists are really like trees.
就会明白为什么跳跃表十分像树
But it's more or less a tree.
其实它多多少少就是一棵树
Let's say at this level, it looks sort of like binary search.
这么看搜索跳跃表就好像二分查找
You look at 14; you look at 15,
我们先找到14 然后找到50
and therefore, you decide whether you are
然后你再决定
in the left half for the right half.
是从左半还是右半开始搜索
And that's sort of like a tree.
这很像一棵树
It's not quite a tree
它在形式上不是树
because we have this element repeated all over.
因为这儿有一大堆重复的元素
But more or less, this is a binary tree.
不过 它差不多就是一棵二叉树
At depth I, we have two to the I nodes,
在第i层有 2^i 个结点
just like a tree, just like a balanced tree.
这就像一棵树 一棵平衡的树
I'm going to call this structure an ideal skip list.
我称这个结构为理想跳跃表
And, if all we are doing our searches,
在搜索的时候
ideal skip lists are pretty good.
理想跳跃表很好使
Maybe at practice: not quite as good as a binary search tree,
它可能没有二叉树那么好
but up to constant factors: just as good.
这跟常数项有关 但总的来说差不多好
So, for example, I mean, we can generalize search,
比如说 额 我们可以总结一下搜索的算法
just check that it's log n.
注意到这里是 log n
So, the search procedure is you start at the top left.
搜索过程是 首先从左上角开始
So, let's say we are looking for 72.
比如说 我们要找72
You start at the top left. 14 is smaller than 72,
首先从左上角开始 14小于72
so I try to go right. 79 is too big.
往右 79太大了
So, I follow this arrow, but I say, oops, that's too much.
我跟着这箭头跑 然后 哦噢 太大了
So, instead, I go down 14 still.
我从14这里下吧
I go to the right: oh, 50, that's still smaller than 72: OK.
往右 50 还好
I tried to go right again. Oh: 79, that's too big.
继续往右 79 太大了
That's no good. So, I go down. So, I get 50.
不行 往下 从50这里
I do the same thing over and over.
如此类推
I try to go to the right: oh, 66, that's OK.
继续往右 66 还好
Try to go to the right: oh, 79, that's too big. So I go down.
再往右 79 太大了 往下
Now I go to the right and, oh, 72: done.
再往右 72 搜索完毕
Otherwise, I'd go too far and try to go down and say,
要不然 我又跑过头了 还想往下
oops, element must not be there.
然后就发现元素肯定不在表中
It's a very simple search algorithm: same as here
这是一个很简单的搜索算法 跟上面写的一样
except just remove the L_1 and L_2.
只要把L1和L2擦了就好
Go right until that would go too far. Then go down.
一直往右跑直到跑过头 然后往下
Then go right until we'd go too far, and then go down.
再一直往右跑直到跑过头 然后往下
You might have to do this log n times.
这可能要重复 log n 次
In each level, you're clearly only walking a couple of steps
在每一层 我们都只需要走几步
because the ratio between these two sizes is only two.
因为每两层的元素数比是2
So, this will cost two log n for search.
所以搜索的代价是 2 log n
Good, I mean, so that was to check
很好 如所欲证
because we were using intuition over here; a little bit shaky.
因为我们这里是用直觉来证的 有点险哈
So, this is an ideal skip list,
现在我们做好了理想跳跃表
we have to support insertions and deletions.
接下来还要支持插入和删除
As soon as we do an insert and delete,
一旦做了插入和删除
there's no way we're going to maintain the structure.
我们就没法维护这个结构
It's a bit too special.
这个结构太特殊了
There is only one of these
这只是众多组合中
where everything is perfectly spaced out,
所有东西都能完美排布的一种
and everything is beautiful. So, we can't do that.
所有东西都很完美 所以我们做不出来
We're going to maintain roughly this structure as best we can.
我们只能大致上尽量地维护这个结构
And, if anyone of you knows
额 如果有谁认识
someone in New York City subway planning,
纽约地铁规划的人
you can tell them this. OK, so: skip lists.
你就可以跟他讲这一套啦 好 这是跳跃表
So, I mean, this is basically our data structure.
这基本上就是我们的数据结构
You could use this as a starting point,
我们可以把它作为出发点
but then you start using skip lists.
但是我们才要真正使用跳跃表
And, we need to somehow implement insertions and deletions,
我们必须要实现插入和删除
and maintain roughly this structure well enough
并且尽量好地维护这个结构
that the search still costs order log n time.
使搜索的代价仍为 O(log n)
So, let's focus on insertions.
现在我们先来研究插入
If we do insertions right,
只要把插入做好了
it turns out deletions are really trivial.
我们就会发现删除是相当普通的
And again, this is all from first principles.
首先 我们仍然从最初的原理出发
We're not allowed to use anything fancy.
不去用其他花哨的东西
But, it would be nice if we used some good chalk.
不过换支好粉笔还是不错的哈
This one looks better.
这支看起来不错
So, suppose you want to insert an element, x.
假设我们要插入元素x
We said how to search for an element. So, how do we insert it?
我们已经讲过怎么搜索元素了 但怎么插入呢
Well, the first thing we should do is figure out where it goes.
首先 我们要找出插入点在哪里
So, we search for x. We call search of x to find
我们先查找x  调用搜索方法来找出
where x fits in the bottom list, not just any list.
x在底链表中的位置 而不是任意一个表
Pretty easy to find out where it fits in the top list.
要找到x在顶链表中的位置很容易
That takes, like, constant time. What we want to know:
这只花费常数的时间 我们想知道的是——
because the top list has constant length,
因为顶链表的长度恒定
we want to know where x goes in the bottom list.
——我们想知道的是x在底链表中的位置
So, let's say we want to insert a search for 80.
比如说我们想插入80
Well, it is a bit too big. Let search for 75.
哦噢 好像有点大 我们来找75吧
So, we'll find the 75 fits right here
我们发现75正好
between 72 and 79 using the same path.
在同一段路上  72和79之间
OK, if it's there already, we complain because I'm going to
好 如果它已经在表中了 那我吐个槽吧
assume all keys are distinct for now
因为我假设所有的键值都是相异的
just so the picture stays simple. But this works fine
为了简单起见 其实没问题
even if you are inserting the same key over and over.
即使你不断插入同样的键值也没问题
So, that seems good.
嗯 看起来很好
One thing we should clearly do is insert x into the bottom list.
我们要做的显然是把x插入到底链表中
We now know where it fits. It should go there.
我们现在知道要插入到哪儿了 应该插入到这里
Because we want to maintain this invariant,
因为我们要保持结构的不变性
that the bottom list contains all the elements.
即底链表包含了所有元素
So, there we go. We've maintained the invariant.
于是我们保持了不变性
The bottom list contains all the elements. So, we search for 75.
底链表中包含所有元素 然后我们找75
We say, oh, 75 goes here, and we just sort of link in 75.
额 75在这里 然后就插入75
You know how to do a linked list, I hope.
我想大家都会插入链表了吧
Let me just erase that pointer.
让我把这指针擦掉
All the work in implementing skip lists
其实所有的跳跃表操作
is the linked list manipulation.
都是链表操作
Is that enough? No, it would be fine for now
这就足够了吗 不 现在看起来还好
because now there's only a chain of length three here
因为现在这段路现在
that you'd have to walk over
也只有三个结点给你走
if you're looking for something in this range.
如果说在这一块搜索的话
But if I just keep inserting 75, and 76, than 76 plus epsilon,
但如果我不断插入75 76 76+ε
76 plus two epsilon, and so on,
76+2ε 等等
just pack a whole bunch of elements in here,
插入一大坨元素
this chain will get really long.
这一段就会变得很长
Now, suddenly, things are not so balanced. If I do a search,
这时 平衡突然就被打破了 我在搜索时
I'll pay an arbitrarily long amount time here to search for someone.
在这一段查找 可能就要花费任意长的时间
If I insert k things, it'll take k time.
如果我插入了k个元素 在这里就要花费k个单位时间
I want it to stay log n.
我希望它保持为 log n
If I only insert log n items, it's OK for now.
如果我只插入 log n 个元素 那么现在还好
What I want to do is decide which of these lists contain 75.
现在我要决定的是 哪几个表中要包含75
So, clearly it goes on the bottom.
首先 显然它要在底链表中
Every element goes in the bottom.
每个元素都出现在底链表中
Should it go up a level? Maybe. It depends. It's not clear yet.
它要不要往上进一级呢 可能吧 看情况 现在还不清楚
If I insert a few items here,
如果我在这儿多插几个元素
definitely some of them should go on the next level.
当然有一些要进入下一级链表
Should I go to levels up? Maybe, but even less likely.
那要不要继续升级呢 可能吧 不过可能性更小
So, what should I do?
那么我应该怎么做
Yeah? [Student]Inaudible.
请说  [学生]。。。
Right, so you maintain the ideal partition size,
没错 我们要保持理想的分节大小
which may be like the length of this chain.
也就是大概这段的长度
And you see, well, if that gets too long,
然后发现 如果它变得太长了
then I should split it in the middle,
我就应该把从它中间分割开
promote that guy up to the next level,
把中位元素提升到上一级
and do the same thing up here.
并往上重复这一步骤
If this chain gets too long
如果相邻两个快线车站
between two consecutive next level express stops,
它们之间的路段太长
then I'll promote the middle guy.
我就提升中位元素
And that's what you'll do in your problem set.
这在你们习题册里面有
That's too fancy for me. I don't need no stinking counters.
这个方法稍微有点复杂  我不需要做什么计数
What else could I do?
我还能怎么做呢
[Student]Inaudible.
[学生]。。。
I could try to maintain the ideal skip list structure.
我可以试着保持理想跳跃表结构
That will be too expensive.
不过这样更新跳跃表代价太高
Like I say, 75 is the guy that gets promoted,
比如说 75被提升了
and this guy gets demoted all the way down.
而这个则相应地被降下来
But that will propagate everything to the right.
但这就要影响到后面的所有元素
And that could cost linear time for update. Other idea?
这要耗费线性时间来更新 还有什么想法
[Student]Inaudible.
[学生]。。。
[Professor]If I only want half of them to go up, I could flip a coin.
[教授]如果我只想让一半的元素获得提升 我可以抛硬币决定
Good idea. All right, for that, I will give you a quarter.
这是一个好主意 很好 五毛请拿好
It's a good one. It's the old line state, Maryland.
这个硬币很值钱的哦亲 它产自红色革命根据地马里兰州
There you go. However, you have to
这是赏给你的  但是
perform some services for that quarter,
你也要帮忙干点活
namely, flip the coin.
那就是抛硬币
Can you flip a coin? Good. What did you get?
你会抛硬币吧 很好 抛出什么来了
Tails, OK, that's the first random bit.
反面 好 这是我们得到的第一个随机数
But we are going to do is build a skip list.
噢 我们现在要构造跳跃表
Maybe I should tell you how first.
我先讲一讲应该怎么做
OK, but the idea is flip a coin.
主要的思想就是抛硬币
If it's heads, so, sorry, if it's heads,
如果抛出的是正面 哦噢现在不是 如果是正面
we will promote it to the next level, and flip again.
我们就提升这个元素 然后再抛一次
So, this is an answer to the question,
这就是刚才问题的答案
which other lists should store x?
x要存在其余的哪个表里
How many other lists should we add x to?
存在多少个表里
Well, the algorithm is, flip a coin,
我们的算法是 先抛硬币
and if it comes out heads, then promote x
如果结果是正面 就提升x
to the next level up, and flip again.
并再抛一次
OK, that's key because we might
这就是问题的关键
want this element to go arbitrarily high.
因为我们想把新元素提升到任意的高度
But for starters, we flip a coin.
首先我们要抛硬币
It doesn't go to the next level.
现在 它没有被提升
Well, we'd like it to go up
我们希望让它
to the next level with probability one half
被提升概率是一半
because we want the ratio between these two sizes to be a half,
因为我们想让两线的长度比是1:2
or sorry, two, depending which way you take the ratio.
或者2:1 看谁比谁
So, I want roughly half the elements up here. So, I flip a coin.
我要提升大约一半的元素  所以我就抛硬币
If it comes up heads, I go up here.
如果抛出正面 我就提升它
This is a fair coin. So I want it 50-50.
所以要用一枚公正的硬币 我让它的概率是50-50
OK, then how many should that element go up to the next level up?
那么 被提升的元素中有多少应被继续提升呢
Well, with 50% probability again. So, I flip another coin.
又是50%喽 我再抛一次硬币
If it comes up heads, I'll go up another level.
如果抛出正面 我就继续提升
And that will maintain the approximate ratio
这样就保持了
between these two guys as being two.
两线长度之比大约为2
The expected ratio will definitely
我们正期望这个比值
be two, and so on, all the way up.
一路往上都约等于2
If I go up to the top and flip a coin,
如果跑到顶层后我再抛硬币
it comes up heads, I'll make another level.
出来的还是正面的话 我就再造一层
This is the insertion algorithm: dead simple.
这就是插入算法 太简单了
The fancier one you will see on your problem set.
刚才说的较复杂的方法 在习题册上有
So, let's do it.
我们动手吧
OK, I also need someone to generate random numbers.
我需要有人来产生随机数
Who can generate random numbers?
谁能生成随机数
Pseudo-random? I'll give you a quarter.
伪随机哈 我也赏你五毛
I have one here. Here you go.
我这儿有 来来来 来来来
That's a boring quarter.
老是给五毛太无趣了
Who would like to generate random numbers?
谁想生成随机数嘛
Someone volunteering someone else:
哈哈 推荐别人
that's a good way to do it. Here you go.
这解决方法真好 给你
You get a quarter, but you're not allowed to flip it.
给你五毛 但不是让你抛
No randomness for you; well, OK, you can generate bits,
不是让你这样搞随机哈 不过你可以先生成随机位
and then compute a number.
再算出一个数
So, give me a number. 44, good answer.
反正给个数字吧 44 很好
OK, we already flipped a coin and I got tails.
我们已经抛过硬币得到反面了
Done. That's the insertion algorithm.
插入完毕 这就是插入算法
I'm going to make some more space actually, put it way down here.
我要多留点位置 写这儿吧
OK, so 44 does not get promoted because we got a tails.
44不能提升 因为我们抛出了反面
So, give me another number.
再给个数字
Nine, OK, I search for nine in this list.
9 先在表中查找9
I should mention one other thing, sorry. I need a small change.
哦对 我还要说明一点 我在这儿做了一点小小的改动
This is just to make sure searches still work.
这是为了保持原有的搜索过程能正常工作
So, the worry is suppose I insert something bigger
我们担心的是 比如说我插入了一个比较大的元素
and then I promote it.
然后提升了它
This would look very bad for a skip list data structure
这个跳跃表的结构就坑爹了
because I always want to start at the top left,
因为我总要从左上角开始搜索
and now there's no top left.
但是左上角没有元素
So, just minor change: just let me remember that.
所以我做点小小的改动 记得刚刚报的是9吧
The minor change is that I'm going to
改动就是 我要把
store a special value minus infinity in every list.
一个特殊值负无穷存到每个表里
So, minus infinity always gets promoted all the way to the top,
也就是说负无穷被一路提升到顶部
whatever the top happens to be now.
无论顶部在哪里
So, initially, that way I'll always have a top left.
这样左上角就一直存在了
Sorry, I forgot to mention that.
忘了提这个 不好意思哈
So, initially I'll just have minus infinity.
所以我一开始先插入一个负无穷
Then I insert 44. I say, OK, 44 goes there, no promotion, done.
然后插入44 那好 44跑到这里 没有提升 插入完毕
Now, we're going to insert nine. Nine goes here.
现在我们插入9 9在这儿
So, minus infinity to nine, flip your coin, heads.
现在负无穷指向9 抛个硬币吧 正面
Did he actually flip it?
他真抛了没有
OK, good. He flipped it before, yeah, sure.
好好好 他之前肯定抛了的
I'm just... giving me a hard time. So, we have nine up here.
如果抛了我不想要的我就惨了 现在我们把9提升到这儿
We need to maintain this minus infinity
我们要保持负无穷在表头
just to make sure it gets promoted along with everything else.
保证它跟着被提升的元素一同提升
So, that looks like a nice skip list.
现在这个跳跃表看起来很和谐
Flip it again. Tails, good.
再抛一次硬币 反面 好
OK, so this looks like an ideal skip list. Isn't that great?
现在它看上去就是理想跳跃表哈 这方法不赖吧
It works every time. OK, give me another number. 26,
每次结果包你满意 再给一个数字 26
OK, so I search for 26. 26 goes here.
好 那我查找26 26应该跑到这儿
It clearly goes on the bottom list.
显然它要在底链表里
Here we go, 26, and then I you raised 44. Flip.
写上26 然后是44 抛吧
Tails, OK, another number. 50, oh, a big one.
反面 好 再给个数字 50 额有点大
It costs me a little while to search, and I get over here. 50.
我要花点时间来搜索 然后跑到这 50
Flip. Heads, good. So 50 gets promoted. Flip it again.
抛 正面 好 50被提升了 再抛
Tails, OK, still a reasonable number.
反面 好 这个结果不错哈
Another number? 12, it takes a little while to get exciting here.
再给个数字 12  还要再过一会儿才会变得更好玩
OK, 12 goes here between nine and 26.
好 12插在9和26中间
You're giving me a hard time here. OK, flip.
你这是在给我制造难度哈 抛吧
Heads, OK, 12 gets promoted.
正面 好 12被提升了
I know you have to work a little bit,
我知道按着程序走还要多走几步
but we just came here to search for 12.
反正现在我们知道12要放在这里
So, we know that nine was the last point we went down.
我们知道9是在往下之前访问的最后一个结点
So, we promote 12. It gets inserted up here.
现在我们提升12 插入到这里
We are just inserting into this particular linked list:
这里我们只是把它插入上面这个链表中
nothing fancy.
没有什么复杂的东西
We link the two twelves together.
然后我们把两个12链接起来
It still looks kind of like a linked list.
这看起来还是像一个链表哈
Flip again. OK, tails, another number. 37. Jeez.
再抛 好 反面 再给个数字 37 额
It's a good test of memory. 37, what was it, 44 and 50?
这在考验我的记忆力 37 然后是 额 44和50
And 50 was at the next level up.
还有50跑到了下一级
I think I should just keep appending elements
我觉得我还是一直往表尾加元素
and have you flip coins.
只让你抛抛硬币更好
OK, we just inserted 37. Tails.
好 我们刚刚插入了37 反面
OK, that's getting to be a long chain.
这条链变得有点长
That looks a bit worse.
看上去不妙
OK, give me another number larger than 50. 51, good answer.
给我一个大于50的数吧 51 很好
Thank you. OK, flip again.（Heads) And again. Tails. Another number.
多谢 再抛（正面） 再抛 反面 再给个数
Wait, someone else should pick a number. It's not working.
等一下 换一个人报数字吧  剧本不是这样写的啊
What did you say? 52, good answer. Flip. Tails, not surprising.
你说啥 52 很好 抛 反面 见怪不怪啦
We've gotten a lot of heads there.
肯定是因为正面太多了
OK, another number. 53, thank you.
再给个数 53 多谢
Flip. Heads, heads, OK. Heads, heads, you didn't flip.
抛 正面吧 正面吧 很好 正面 正面 你都没抛
All right, 53, you get the idea.
好好好 53 你懂的
If you get two consecutive heads,
如果连续抛出两个正面
then the guy goes up two levels.
就把元素提升两级
OK, now flip for real.
现在真的抛一个
Heads. Finally. Heads we've been waiting for.
正面 盼星星盼月亮终于等到了
If you flipped three heads in a row, you go three levels.
如果连续抛出三个正面 就把元素提升三级
And each time, we keep promoting minus infinity.
注意每次都要提升负无穷
Look again. Heads, oh my God. Where were they before?
再抛 正面 额滴神啊 你们刚刚都跑哪儿去了
Flip again. It better be tails this time. Tails, good.
再抛 这次最好是反面 反面 太好了
OK, you get the idea. Eventually you run out of board space.
大家都懂了 最后我们都画到黑板外面去了
Now, it's pretty rare that you go too high.
注意 升到很高的可能性是很小的
What's the probability that you go higher than log n?
高于 log n 的概率是多少呢
Another easy log computation.
还是简单的对数运算
Each time, I have a 50% probability of going up.
每次我都有50%的提升概率
One in n probability of going up log n levels
提升 log n 的概率是1/n
because half to the power of log n is one out of n.
因为(1/2)^(log n)=1/n
So, it depends on n, but I'm not going to go too high.
所以它跟n有关 当然我不想它跑太高
And, intuitively, this is not so bad. So, these are skip lists.
直观上 这个结果并不坏 这就是跳跃表
You have the ratios right in expectation,
提升概率与期望相符
which is a pretty weak statement.
但这只是一个很弱的结论
This doesn't say anything about the lengths of these change.
它不涉及生成的这些区段的长度
But intuitively, it's pretty good.
但直观上还是很不错的
Let's say pretty good on average.
我们说它平均来看还挺好的
So, I had two semi-random processes going on here.
在插入的时候 发生了两个半随机过程
One is picking the numbers, and that,
一个是选数的过程
I don't want to assume anything about.
对此我不作任何假设
The numbers could be adversarial. It could be sequential.
输入数列可以凌乱的 也可以是顺序的
It could be reverse sorted. It could be random. I don't know.
可以是逆序的 可以是随机的 我也不知道
So, it didn't matter what he said.
所以他报什么数都无所谓
At least, it shouldn't matter.
至少不应该跟它有关
I mean, it matters here. Don't worry. You're still loved.
当然上课的时候要你帮忙啦 别担心 我还是很疼你滴
You still get your $0.25.
你可以留着那两毛五
But what the algorithm cares about is
但是算法真正关心的是
the outcomes of these coins.
抛硬币的结果
And the probability, the statement that
还有概率 这个命题——
this data structure is fast with high probability
“这个数据结构执行速度快是有高概率的”
is only about the random coins.
——只对随机抛硬币的情况成立
Right, it doesn't matter what the adversary chooses for numbers
对方选择任何输入数据都无所谓
as long as those coins are random,
只要抛硬币结果是随机的
and the adversary doesn't know the coins.
对方不知道抛硬币的结果
It doesn't know the outcomes of the coins.
算法在抛之前不知道结果
So, in that case, on average,
这样平均来看
overall of the coin flips, you should be OK.
在大量抛硬币的情况下 它还是好用的
But the claim is not just that it's pretty good on average.
但按我们的说法 它不只是平均来看挺好
But, it's really, really good almost always.
而是几乎总是很好很好
OK, with really high probability it's log n.
即有高概率为 O(log n)
So, for example, with probability, one minus one over n,
举个例子 有1-1/n的概率
it's order of log n,
1-1/n的概率 它是O(log n)
with probability one minus one over n^2 it's log n,
或者有1-1/n^2的概率  它是O(log n)
probability one minus one over n^100, it's order log n.
或者有1-1/n^100的概率 它是O(log n)
All those statements are true for any value of 100.
这一命题对100以内任意幂次都成立
So, that's where we're going.
这是我们要证明的
OK, I should mention, how do you delete in a skip list?
额 我还没讲怎么从跳跃表中删除元素
Find the element. You delete it all the way.
找到这个元素 把它从出现的链表中一路删上去
There's nothing fancy with delete.
删除操作没有什么高级的东西
Because we have all these independent, random choices,
因为前面的所有操作都是独立的随机的
all of these elements are sort of independent from each other.
所有元素都相互独立
We don't really care. So, delete an element, just throw it away.
我们不用操心太多 所以删除元素就直接扔掉它
The tricky part is insertion. When I insert an element,
有技巧的部分是插入 插入的时候
I'm just going to randomly see how high it should go.
我要随机地确定它能跑多高
With probability one over two to the i, it will go to height i.
它有 1/2^i 的概率跑到第i层
Good, that's my time. I've been having too much fun here.
好 我看看时间 前面我们太欢乐了
I've got to go a little bit faster, OK.
后面我们要讲快点
So here's the theorem.
下面是要证的定理
Let's see exactly what we are proving first.
我们看看要证明什么
With high probability,
有高概率——
this is a formal notion which I will define a second.
这是一个正式的概念 我一会儿就来定义它
Every search in n elements skip lists costs order of log n.
——使在有n个元素的跳跃表里 每次搜索时间为 O(log n)
So, that's the theorem.
这就是定理
Now I need to define with high probability.
现在我来定义“有高概率”
So, with high probability.
那么 “有高概率”
And, it's a bit of a long phrase. So, often we will,
这个词儿有点长 我们常常
and you can abbreviate it WHP.
缩写为W.H.P.
So, if I have a random event, and the random event here is that
假如有一个随机事件 在这里随机事件就是
every search in an n element skip list costs order log n,
在有n个元素的跳跃表里 每次搜索时间为 O(log n)
I want to know what it means
我们来看看
for that event E to occur with high probability.
这一事件E“有高概率”发生是什么意思
So this is the definition.
这是定义
So, the statement is that
“有高概率”是指
for any alpha greater than or equal to one,
对于任意大于等于1的α
there is a suitable choice of constants
存在适宜的常数
for which the event, E,
使事件E的概率
occurs with this probability I keep mentioning.
为我之前一直提到的
So, the probability at least one minus one over n to the alpha.
概率至少为1-O(1/n^α)
So, this is a bit imprecise,
这个定义不是很准确
but it will suffice for our purposes.
但对我们的证明来说够用了
If you want to really formal definition,
如果你想要更正式的定义
you can read the lecture notes.
可以阅读课程注记
There are special lecture notes
我们官网上
for this lecture on the stellar site.
有我们课程的特别注释
And, there's the PowerPoint notes on the SMA site.
SMA课程网站上也有 PowerPoint 格式的注记
But, right, there's a bit of a subtlety
好 这个常数的选择
in the choice of constants here.
是一件很微妙的事
There is a choice of this constant.
这个常数是可以任意选取的
And there's a choice of this constant.
这个常数也是可以任意选取的
And, these are related.
当然它们是相关的
And, there's alpha, which we get to whatever we want.
α我们可以取到任意一个值
But the bottom line is,
但我们的底线是
we get to choose what probability we want this to be true.
我们要选择一个能让定理成立的概率
If I want it to be true,
如果我希望
with probability one minus one over n^100, I can do that.
它的成功概率是1-1/n^100 这是可以做到的
I just said alpha to a hundred, and up to this little constant
我只要令α=100 再选取适宜的常数
that's going to grow much slower than n to the alpha.
使它的增长速度远远慢于n^α
I get the error probability.
由此我得到失败概率
So this thing is called the error probability.
这叫失败概率
The probability that I fail is polynomially small,
失败概率就会多项式级地小
for any polynomial I want.
多项式阶数可以任意小
Now, with the same data structure, right,
对于同一个数据结构
I fixed the data structure. It doesn't depend on alpha.
固定一个数据结构 它与α无关
Anything you want, any alpha value you want,
无论输入是什么 无论α等于多少
this data structure will take order of log n time.
数据结构都要花费 O(log n) 的时间
Now, this constant will depend on alpha.
现在这个常数是跟α有关的
So, you know, you want error probability one over n^100
比如说 我们想让失败概率为 1/n^100
is probably going to be, like, 100 log n. It's still log n.
那就是 100 O(log n) 那还是 O(log n) 嘛
OK, this is a very strong claim
好 这是一个很强的断言
about the tail of the distribution of the running time of search
控制了搜索时间分布的末端
Very strong.
非常强
Let me give you an idea of how strong it is.
我来告诉大家很强是什么概念
How many people know what Boole's inequality is?
有多少人知道布尔不等式
How many people know what the union bound is in probability?
多少人知道并事件的概率上界
You should. It's in appendix c.
你们应该会的 这些内容在附录c里
Maybe you'll know it by the theorem.
可能你从定理里就看出来了
It's good to know it by name.
它从字面上很容易理解
It's sort of like linearity of expectations.
它有点像期望的线性性
It's a lot easier to communicate to someone.
讲这个别人更容易明白
Linearity of expectations: instead of saying,
一提到期望的线性性
you know that thing where you sum up
你就会想到
all the expectations of things,
事件期望之和
and that's the expectation of the sum?
等于总事件的期望
It's a lot easier to say linearity of expectation.
讲期望的线性性省事多了
So, let me quiz you in a different way.
现在我换个方式来问
So, if I take a bunch of events,
我来取一堆事件
and I take their union,
然后取它的并
either this happens or this happens, or so on.
这个事件发生或这个事件发生或等等
So, this is the inclusive OR of k events.
这是k个事件的并
And, instead, I look at
另一方面 考察
the sum of the probabilities of those events.
这些事件期望之和
OK, easy question: are these equal?
一个简单的问题 它们相等吗
No, unless they are independent.
不等 除非事件相互独立
But can I say anything about them, any relation?
但我能断定它们的关系吗
Smaller, yeah. This is less than or equal to that.
小于等于 对 上边小于等于下边
OK, this should be intuitive to you
这直观上是正确的
from a probability point of view.
用概率的观点看
Look at the textbook.
翻书去吧
OK: very basic result, trivial result almost.
这是一个基本的结果 挺普通的
What does this tell us?
这说明什么
Well, suppose that E_i is some kind of error event.
假设 E_i 是某个失败事件
We don't want it to happen.
我们不希望它发生
OK, and suppose, mix some letters here.
i这里可能又用混了
Suppose I have a bunch of events
假设我有一堆事件
which occur with high probability.
是有高概率的
OK, call those E_i complement.
额 把它叫做 E_i 的对立
So, suppose, so this is the end of that statement,
我们最后可以推出
E_i complement occurs with high probability.
E_i 的对立是有高概率的
OK, so then the probability of E_i
所以 E_i 的概率很小
is very small, polynomially small.
多项式级地小
One over n to the alpha for any alpha I want.
小于O(1/n^α) 对任意α成立
Now, suppose I take a whole bunch of these events,
现在 假设我取一大堆这样的事件
and let's say that k is polynomial in n.
k个事件 k是n的多项式
So, I take a bunch of events, which I'd like to happen.
取一大堆我想要发生的事件
They all occur with high probability.
它们都是有高概率的
There is only polynomially many of them.
它们只有多项式那么多个
So let's say, let me give this constant a name. Let's call it c.
现在我们明确地定义这个常数 设它为c
Let's say I take n to the c such events.
我们说取 n^c 个事件
Well, what's the probability that
那么 所有事件同时发生
all those events occur together?
——这概率是多少？
Because they should most of the time occurred together
因为 额 它们大多数情况下同时发生
because each one occurs most of the time,
因为任意一个在大多数情况下都会发生
occurs with high probability.
是有高概率的
So, I want to look at E_1 bar intersect, E_2 bar, and so on.
也就是 我想考察 E_1— 交 E_2— 等等等等
So, each of these occurs as high probability.
每个事件都有高概率
What's the chance that they all occur?
它们同时发生的概率是多少
It's also with high probability. I'm changing the alpha.
它们同时发生也是有高概率的 我取不同的α
So, the union bound tells me
因此 并事件的概率告诉我们
the probability of any one of these failing,
任意一个事件失败的概率
the probability of this failing,
它失败的概率
or this failing, or this failing,
它失败的概率 或它失败的概率
which is this thing, is, at most,
也就是它 至多
the sum of the probabilities of each failure.
是它们各自失败的概率之和
These are the error probabilities.
这就是失败概率
I know that each of them is,
我知道任意一个的失败概率
at most, one over n to the alpha, with a constant in front.
至多是 1/n^α 带个常数
If I add them all up, there's only n to the c of them.
如果我把它们加起来 至多有 n^c 个
So, I take this error probability, and I multiply by n to the c.
我取一个失败概率 然后乘上 n^c
So, I get like n to the c over n to the alpha,
得到 n^c/n^α
which is one over n to the alpha minus c.
即 1/n^(α-c)
I can set alpha as big as I want.
α可任意大
So, I said it much, much bigger than c,
我就让它远远大于c
and this event occurs with high probability.
所以这一事件是有高概率的
I sort of made a mess here,
这儿写得有点乱
but this event occurs with high probability because of this.
总之 因此 这一事件是有高概率的
Whatever the constant is here, however many events I'm taking,
不管这常数是啥 不管我取多少事件
I just set alpha to be bigger than that.
我取α比它大就行了
And, this event will occur with high probability, too.
并事件也是有高概率的
So, when I say here that
所以 当我说
every search of cost order log n with high probability,
每次搜索耗费 O(log n) 是有高概率的时候
not only do I mean that if you look at one search,
我不仅是指考察一次搜索
it costs order log n with high probability.
它耗费 O(log n) 有高概率
You look at another search,
再考察另一次搜索
and it costs log n with high probability.
它耗费 O(log n) 也有高概率
I mean, if you take every search,
而是 考察每一次搜索
all of them take order log n time with high probability.
全部搜索都耗费 O(log n) 也有高概率
So, this event that every single search you do takes order log n,
从而 每次搜索都花费 O(log n)
is true with high probability.
是有高概率的
Assuming the number of searches you are doing is polynomial in n.
假设搜索的次数为n的多项式
So, I'm assuming that I'm not using this data structure forever,
也就是说 我假设我不是要把这数据结构用无数次
just for a polynomial amount of time.
只是使用多项式级的时间而已
But, who's got more than a polynomial amount of time anyway?
但又有谁有比多项式级还多的时间呢？
This is MIT. So, hopefully that's clear.
这里可是 MIT  那就没问题了
We'll see it a few more times. Yeah?
我们以后还会见到它 请提问
[Student]Inaudible.
[学生]。。。
[Professor]The algorithm doesn't depend on Alpha.
[教授]这个算法并不依赖α
The question is how do you choose alpha in the algorithm.
问题是在分析算法时如何选择α
So, we don't need to. This is just sort of for an analysis tool.
所以我们不需要考虑它 它只是一个分析的工具
This is saying that the farther out you get,
它的意思是多项式增长得越大
so you say, well, what's the probability that more than ten log n.
比如说 额 大于 10 log n 的概率是多少
Well, it's like one over n^10. Let's say it's linear.
打个比方 大概是 1/n^10 假设概率是线性增长的
Well, what's the chance that you're more than 20 log n?
也就是说 大于 20 log n 的概率是多少
Well that's one over n^20.
比方说 那就成了 1/n^20
So, the point is the tail of this distribution
意思就是说 在概率分布的尾部
is getting a really small, really fast.
概率会非常迅速地收敛到非常小
And, such using alpha is more like
引入α只是为了
sort of for your own feeling good.
方便论述和证明
OK, you can set it to 100, and then n is at least two.
你可以令α=100 然后要求n至少为2
So, that's like one over 2^100 chance that you fail.
那失败概率大概只有 1/2^100
That's damn small. If you've got a real random number generator,
那小得不得了 如果你有个真随机数生成器
the chance that you're going to
生成一个大于 2^100 的数
hit one over 2^200 is pretty tiny, right?
概率是很小的 对吧
So, let's say you set alpha to 256,
再如 令α=256
which is always a good number.
256是个好数字
2^256 is much bigger than
2^256 远远大于
the number of particles in the known universe,
宇宙中已知粒子的总数
so, the light matter.
除了暗物质哈
So, actually I think this
其实我想
even accounts for some notion of dark matter.
把暗物质也包括进来也未必有这个数
So, this is really, really, really big.
所以这个数非常非常非常大
So, the chance that you pick a random particle in the universe
也就是说 你在宇宙中随机挑出一个粒子
that happens to be your favorite particle, this one right here,
正好是你最喜欢的那个粒子的概率 这个哈
that's over one over 2^256, or even smaller.
应该大于 1/2^256  或者更小
So, set alpha to 256, the chance to your algorithm
所以 令α=256 此时我们的算法
takes more than order log n time is a lot smaller
花费的时间长于 O(log n)的概率
than the chance that a meteor
远远小于一颗流星
strikes your computer at the same time
正好砸在你的电脑上 而且同时
that it has a floating point error,
电脑出了个浮点运算错误 又同时
at the same time that the earth explodes
地球君爆炸了
because they're putting a transport through this part
因为不知道谁要修条高速公路
of the solar system at the same time,
正好路过太阳系 又同时
I mean, I could go on, right?
我可以继续讲一大堆
It's really, really unlikely that you are more than log n.
总之时间超过 O(log n) 的机会是非常非常小的
And how unlikely: you get to choose.
至于有多小 任君选择
But it's just in the analysis the algorithm doesn't depend on it.
但这只是在分析中用到 算法并不依赖于α
It's the same algorithm, very cool.
算法还是那个算法 犀利不？
Sometimes, with high probability, bounds depends on alpha.
有时 某些有高概率的定理 时间的界与α有关
I mean, the algorithm depends on alpha. But here, it will not.
也就是说算法依赖于α 不过这里不是
OK, away we go. So now you all understand the claim.
我们继续 现在大家都明白这个说法是什么意思
So let's do a warm up. We will also need this fact.
先做点准备 我们需要如下事实
But it's pretty easy. The lemma is that with high probability,
很简单的 引理是 有高概率——
the number of levels in the skip list is order log n.
——使跳跃表的层数为 O(log n)
I think it's order log n, certainly.
是 O(log n) 没错吧 就是它了
So, how do we prove that something happens with high probability?
怎么证明一个事件发生是有高概率的
Compute the probability that it happened; show that it's high.
计算它的概率 说明它很高
Even if you don't know what high probability means,
就算我们不懂什么叫有高概率
in fact, I used to ask that earlier on.
其实 我刚才应该先问的
So, let's compute the chance that it doesn't happen,
也就是说 计算它不发生的概率
the error probability,
失败概率
because that's just a one minus the cleaner.
然后成功概率就等于用一去减它
So, I'd like to say, let's say,
所以 我说
that it's, at most, c log n levels.
它至多有 c log n 层
So, what's the error probability for that event?
它的失败概率是多少
This is sort of an event.
这是个随机事件
I'll put it in squiggles just for, all set.
加个花括号 表示全体事件的集合
This is the probability that
这就是层数
they are strictly greater than c log n levels.
严格大于 c log n 的概率
So, I want to say that
我想证明的是
that probability is particularly small, polynomially small.
这个概率很小 多项式级地小
Well, how do I make levels?
那么 分层是怎么产生的呢
When I insert an element, the probability half, it goes up.
当我插入元素的时候 大概有一半的概率被提升
And, the number of levels in the skip list
并且 跳跃表的层数
is the max over all the elements of how high it goes up.
是所有元素可能达到的高度的最大值
But, max, oh, that's a mess.
不过 说到最大值 那可乱套了
All right, you can compute the expectation of the max
还好 我们可以计算最大值的期望
if you have a bunch of unknown variables;
如果我们有一大堆未知变量
there is expectation there is a constant, and you take the max.
算出期望 带上常数 然后取最大值
It's like log n in expectation,
期望我们知道是 O(log n)
but we want a much stronger statement.
但是我们想要一个更强的结果
And, we have this Boole's inequality
我们用布尔不等式
that says I have a bunch of things,
来描述一堆元素
polynomially many things. Let's say we have n items.
多项式多个元素 比如说有n个元素
Each one independently, I don't even care if it's a dependent.
它们相互独立 甚至我不关心它们有没有依赖关系
But each one potentially goes up some amount.
但每个都有被提升的可能
If it goes up more than c log n,
如果某一个升了多于 c log n 级
yeah, the number of levels is more than c log n.
那跳跃表的层数就大于 c log n
So, this is, at most, and then I want to know,
然后这个小于等于 额 然后我想知道
do any of those events happen for any of the n elements?
这n个元素中是否有被提升的
So, I just multiplied by n.
所以我乘上n
It's certainly, at most,
这个当然小于等于
n times the probability that x gets promoted,
n乘上x的提升概率
this much here, greater than or equal to log n times.
提升多少呢 提升大于等于 log n层
OK, if I pick, for any element, x,
对于任意的元素x
because it's the same for each element.
因为所有的元素都一样
They are done independently.
它们的提升是相互独立的
So, I'm just summing over x here,
即 我只是对x求和
and that's just a factor of n. Clear?
得到因子n 明白吧
This is Boole's inequality.
这用到布尔不等式
Now, what's the probability that x gets promoted c log n times?
那么 x被提升 c log n 次的概率是多少
We did this before for log n. It was one over n.
我们已经对 log n 的情况推导过了 1/n
For c log n, it's one over n to the c. OK, this is n times two.
对于c log n 那就是 1/n^c 那就是n乘上2
Let's be nicer: one half to the power of c log n.
写清楚一点 (1/2)^(c log n)
One half to the power of c log n is one over two to the c log n.
(1/2)^(c log n)=1/2^(c log n)
The log n comes out here, becomes an n.  We get n to the c.
log n 提出来 分子变成n  得到n^c
So, this is n divided by n to the c,
即 n/n^c
which is n to the c minus one.
即 n^(c-1)
And, I get to choose c to be whatever I want.
c是任意选择的
So, I choose c minus one to be alpha. I think exactly that.
令 c-1=α 我想是这样吧
Oh, sorry, one over n to the c minus one. Thank you.
哦 抱歉 这里是1/n^(c-1) 多谢
It better be small. This is an upper bound.
它最好是个很小的数哈 因为这可是上界
So, probability is polynomially small. I get to choose,
所以 概率是多项式地小的 我只要取适宜的常数就好了
and this is a bit of the trick.
这里稍微有一点技巧
I'm choosing this constant to be large, large enough for alpha.
我令这个常数对α足够大
The point is, as c grows, alpha grows.
关键是 随着c增长 α也增长
Therefore, I can set alpha to be whatever I want,
所以 我令α取定任意一个值时
set c accordingly.
c可以相应取值满足条件
So, there's a little bit more words that have to go here.
这里还有点文字表述
But, they're in the notes.
它们都在课堂注记里了
I can set alpha to be as large as I want.
我可以让α任意大
So, I can make this probability
从而我可以让概率
as small as I want in the polynomial sets.
在多项式集合内任意小
So, that's it. Number of levels, order log n: wasn't that easy?
证毕 层数为 O(log n) 很简单吧
Rules and equality, the point is that when you're dealing
基本规则和等式推导 关键是
with high probability, use Boole's inequality.
处理“有高概率”的时候 运用布尔不等式
And, anything that's true for one element
还有 对某一个元素成立的结论
is true for all of them, just like that.
对所有的元素也成立 就是这样
Just lose a factor of n, but that's just one in the alpha,
只是放大一下 乘上因子n 那只是α次幂里的一次啊
and alpha is big: big constant, but it's big.
α是一个很大的常数 非常大
OK, so let's prove the theorem.
下面我们来证明定理
High probability searches cost order log n.
有高概率使搜索代价为 O(log n)
We now know the height is order log n,
我们现在知道跳跃表的高度是 O(log n)
but it depends how balanced this thing is.
不过这取决于链表是否均衡
It depends how long the chains are
它取决于一节的长度有多少
to really know that a search costs log n.
才能确定一次搜索的代价是 O(log n)
Just knowing a bound on the height is not enough,
仅仅知道高度的界是不够的
unlike a binary tree.
不像二叉树
So, we have one cool idea for this analysis.
现在 我们有一个很酷的想法完成这个分析
And it's called backwards analysis.
称为回溯分析
So, normally you think of a search
一般来讲 我们说搜索
as starting in the top left corner
是从左上角开始
going left[right] and down until you get to
向右向下前进
the item that you're looking for.
直到找到查找的元素
I'm going to look at the reverse process.
我现在反过来看
You start at the item you're looking for,
我们从要查找的元素开始
and you go left and up until you get to the top left corner.
向左向上前进 直到到达左上角
The number of steps in those two walks is the same.
两种路径经过的步数应该是一样的
And, I'm not implementing an algorithm here,
我这里不是实现算法
I'm just doing analysis.
只是做分析
So, those are the same processes, just in reverse.
这是两个相同的过程 只是反过来而已
So, here's what it looks like. You have a search,
所以是这样的 我们做一次搜索
and it starts, which really means that
从底链表上某结点开始
it ends at a node in the bottom list.
实际上是搜索结束
Then, each time you visit a node in this search,
然后 每一次访问新的结点
you either go left or up.
都是向左或向上访问得到的
And, when do you go left or up?
那么什么时候往左 什么时候往上呢
Well, it depends with the coin flip was.
那就取决于抛硬币的结果
So, if the node wasn't promoted at this level.
也就是说 如果结点在这一层没有被提升
So, if it wasn't promoted higher,
没有被提升到更高
and that happened exactly when we got a tails.
那是我们抛出反面时发生的事情
Then, we go left, which really means we came from the left.
那我们就向左 因为搜索的时候是从左边过来的
Or, if we got a heads,
反过来 如果我们抛出正面
so if this node was promoted to the next level,
那结点被提升到下一级
which happened whenever we got a heads at that particular moment.
这是我们抛出正面时发生的事情
This is in the past some time when we did the insertion.
我们是在原先插入的时候抛的硬币
Then we go, or came from, up. And, we stop at the root.
正面我们就向上走 或者说搜索的时候是从上面来 最终回到根结点
This is really where we start; same thing.
那是我们搜索的起点 那是一个意思
So, either at the root or I'm also going to think of this
我们停在根结点 或者说
as stopping at minus infinity.
停在负无穷
OK, that was a bit messy, but let me review.
写得有点乱 我们重新过一遍
So, normally we start up here.
通常来说我们是从这儿开始的
Well, just looking at everything backwards,
我们倒推整个过程
and in brackets is what's really happening.
括号里面的是真正的搜索过程
So, this search ends at the node you were looking for.
搜索结束在要查找的结点上
It's always in the bottom list.
它总是在底链表里
Then it says, well, was this node promoted higher?
然后我们考虑 这个结点被提升了吗
If it was, I came from above. If not, I came to the left.
若是 我是从上边来的 若不是 我是从左边来的
It must have been in the bottom chain somewhere.
它一定是在底链表的某处
OK, and that's true at every node you visit.
这对任意一个被访问过的结点都成立
It depends whether that quite slipped heads or tails
取决于抛硬币的结果是正面还是反面
at the time that you inserted that node into that level.
注意是在这一层做结点插入的时候抛的那次
But, these are just a bunch of events. I'm just going to check,
因为我们一堆事件 我现在考虑
what is the probability that it's heads,
正面的概率是多少
and what is the probability that it's tails?
反面的概率是多少
It's always a half. Every time I look at a coin flip,
总是一半对一半 每次抛硬币的时候
when it was flipped,
硬币被抛出的时候
there was a probability of half going out of their way.
自然就有一半对一半的概率
That's the magic.
很神奇吧
And, I'm not using that these events are independent anyway.
这里我没有用到事件的独立性
For every element that I search for,
对于我搜索的任一个元素
for every value, x, that's another search.
任一个值x 都是单一一次搜索
Those events may not be independent.
这些事件可能不是独立的
I can still use Boole's inequality and conclude that
我仍然可以使用布尔不等式推出
all of them are order log n with high probability.
它们都是 O(log n)的情况 是有高概率的
As long as I can prove that
只要我能证明
any one event happens with high probability.
任意一个事件发生是有高概率的
So, I don't need independence between,
我不需要每次搜索之间的独立性
I knew that these coin flips in a single search are independent,
我知道给定一次搜索 全部抛硬币的结果是相互独立的
but everything else, for different searches I don't care.
但对其他的东西 对不同的搜索来看 我不需要什么条件
So, how long can this process go on?
那么 这个搜索过程能持续多长呢
We want to know how many times can I make this walk?
我们想知道搜索过程要走几步
Well, when I hit the root node, I'm done.
注意只要我回到根结点 搜索就结束
Well, how quickly would I hit the root node?
那么我回到根结点要多久呢
Well, with probability, a half, I go up each step.
在每一步向上走的概率是一半
The number of times I go up is,
我向上走的次数
at most, the number of levels minus one.
至多为层数减1
And that's order log n with high probability.
层数有高概率为 O(log n)
So, this is the only other idea.
这是我们用到的另一个条件
So, we are now proving this theorem.
现在我们来证明定理
So, the number of up moves in a search,
证明 在一次搜索时向上走的次数
which are really down moves, but same thing,
实际是向下走 一样啦
is less than the number of levels.
小于层数
Certainly, you can't go up
这是自然的 我们不能
more than there are levels in the search.
在搜索中跑得比总层数还高
And in insert, you can go arbitrarily high.
在插入的时候 我们才能跑到任意高
But a search: as high as you can go.
但在搜索时 最高不能超过层数
And this is, at most, c log n with high probability.
那就是 有高概率至多为 c log n 层
This is what we proved in the lemma.
这是我们在引理中已经证明了的
So, we have a bound on the number of up moves.
所以 我们得到了上行次数的上界
Half of the moves, roughly, are going to be up moves.
大约有一半的访问是上行访问
So, this pretty much bounds to the number of moves.
这大致给出了总步数的界
Not quite. So, what this means is that with high probability,
但这不是严格的 是有高概率的
so this is the same probability,
上行和左行有同样的概率
but I could choose that as high
但我在搜索中可以跑得足够高
as I want by setting c large enough.
只要我令c充分大
The number of moves, in other words, the cost of the search
总访问数 换句话说 搜索的代价
is at most the number of coin flips
至多是我们累计抛出 c log n 个正面时
until we get c log n heads, right,
总的抛硬币的次数
because in every step of the search, I make a move,
因为在搜索的每一步 我移动一个结点
and then I flip another coin, conceptually.
正好对应一次抛硬币
There is another independent coin lying there.
每次抛的硬币是相互独立的
And it's either heads or tails. Each of those is independent.
要么是正面要么是反面 是相互独立的
So, how many independent coin flips does it take
那么我要抛多少次硬币
until I get c log n heads?
才能抛出 c log n 个正面呢
The claim is that that's order log n with high probability.
我们断言它有高概率为 O(log n)
But we need to prove that. So, this is a claim.
这是需要证明的 这是我们的断言
So, if you just sit there with a coin,
现在假设你就坐在那儿拿着个硬币
and you want to know how many times does it take
你想知道要抛多少次
until I get c log n heads, the claim is that
才能得出 c log n 个正面 而我们的断言是
that number is order log n with high probability.
有高概率是 O(log n)
As long as I prove that,
只要我证明了这个
I know that the total number of steps I make,
我就知道搜索的总步数
which is the number of heads and tails is order log n
也就是正面和反面的总数是 O(log n)
because I definitely know the number of heads is,
因为我已经知道正面的数目是
at most, c log n.
至多 c log n
The claim is that the number of tails can't be too much bigger.
我们断言 反面的个数不可能多出太多
Notice, I can't just say c here.
注意 这里我不能只写上c
OK, it's really important that I have log n. Why?
有个 log n 是很重要的 为什么
Because with high probability, it depends on n.
因为“有高概率”依赖于n
This notion depends on n.
这个概念是依赖于n的
Log n: it's true. Anything bigger that log n: it's true, like n.
对log n 这是对的 对于大于 log n 的表达式它也成立 比如 n
If I put n here, this is also true.
我在这放上n 那也是对的
But, if I put a constant or a log log n, this is not true.
但是 如果我写的是常数 或者 log log n 那就不对了
It's really important that I have log n here
log n 是很重要的
because my notion of high probability
因为“有高概率”的定义
depends on what's written here.
依赖于这个式子是什么
OK, it's clear so far. We're almost done,
这个断言解释明白了 我们马上要证出来了
which is good because I just ran out of time.
太好了 因为我快要没时间了
Sorry, we're going to go a couple minutes over.
不好意思 我们要拖堂几分钟
So, I want to compute the error probability here.
现在我来计算失败概率
So, I want to compute the probability that
我想计算一下
there is less than c log n heads.
抛出少于 c log n 个正面的概率
Let me skip this step. So, I will be approximate and say,
这步骤我就跳过了 大致上 我是说
what's the probability that there is, at most, c log n heads?
至多有 c log n 个正面的概率是多少
So, I need to say how many coins we are flipping here
我需要知道总共抛了多少次硬币
for what this event is.
对应这一事件
So, I need to specify this constant.
所以我要明确给出这个常数
Let's say we flip ten c log n coins.
我们说 总共抛了 10c log n 个硬币
Now I want to look at the error probability under that event.
现在我来考虑它的失败概率
The probability that there is at most c log n heads
在 10c log n 次抛硬币中
among those ten c log n flips.
至多 c log n 个正面的概率为
So, the claim is this should be pretty small.
我们断言它很小
It's going to depend on ten.
其实跟这里的10有关
Then I'll choose ten to be arbitrarily large,
然后我令10这个位置的常数任意大
and I'll be done, OK, make my life a little bit easier.
然后证完 接下来的工作就简单些了
Well, I would ask you normally, but this is 6.042 material.
我应该提问的 但这是6.042课程的内容
So, what's the probability that we have,
那么至多有那么多正面的
at most, this many heads?
这个概率是多少？
Well, that means that nine c log n of the coins,
也就是说 有 9c log n 的硬币
because there are ten c log n flips, c log n heads at most,
因为一共 10c log n 个硬币 至多 c log n 个正面
nine c log n at least better be tails.
至少 9c log n 个反面
So this is the probability that all those other guys become tails,
这是那么多个硬币是反面的概率
which is already pretty small.
这已经很小了
And then, there is this permutation thing.
然后这里还有个组合数
So, if I had exactly c log n heads, this would be
如果我要求正好有 c log n 个正面
the number of ways to rearrange c log n heads
有这么多种方式
among ten c log n coin flips.
从 10c log n 中选择 c log n 个为正面
OK, that's just the number of permutations.
这个是组合数
So, this is a bit big, which is kind of annoying.
数字有点大 很烦人
This is really, really small.
这一项又很小很小
The claim is this is much smaller than that is big.
我们断言这项的减小远远快于这项的增大
So, this is just some math. I'm going to whiz through it.
这都是数学推导 我很快地过一下
So, you don't have to stay too long. But you should go over it.
大家不会等太久 但还是过一下
You should know that y choose x is,
我们知道 组合数(y,x)
at most, ey over x to the x, good fact.
不大于 (ey/x)^x 这个事实很好用
Therefore, this is, at most, ten c log n over c log n,
因此 这个不大于 10c log n/c log n
also known as ten.
也就是10
These cancel. There's an e out here.
消掉这些 这里还有个e
And then I raise that to the c log n power.
然后写上 c log n 次幂
OK, then I divide by two to the power, nine c log n.
除上 2^(9c log n)
OK, so what's this?
这是啥
This is e times ten to the c log n
这是 (10e)^(c log n)
divided by two to the nine c log n.
除以 2^(9c log n)
OK, claim this is very big. This is not so big,
我们说 这个很大 这个不那么大
because I have a nine here. So, let's work it out.
因为这里有个9 我们推一下
This e times ten, that's a good number, we can put upstairs.
这是 10e 这个数字很好 放在乘幂上面
So, we get log of e times ten, ten times, e, and then c log n.
我们得到 log (10e) 然后是 c log n
And then, we have over two to the nine c log n.
除以 2^(9c log n)
So, we have this two to the c log n in both cases.
分子分母都有 2^(c log n)
So, this is two to the log,
得到 2^((log(10e)-9)c log n)
ten e minus nine, c, log n: some basic algebra.
这是基本的运算哈
So, I'm going to set, not quite.
现在我让 额 先不搞这个
This is one over two to the nine minus log:
这等于 1/2^(9-log...）
so, just inverting everything here, negating the sign in here.
反过来写 变个号
And, this is my alpha because the rest is n.
然后就可以令这个为α 因为剩下的就是n
So, this is one over n to the alpha
这就是1/n^α
when alpha is this particular value:
我已经令α为
nine minus log of ten times e times c.
(9-log(10e))c
It's a bit of a strange thing. But, the point is,
这看起来有点怪 但关键是
as ten goes to infinity,
随着10这里的常数趋于无穷
nine here is the number one smaller than ten, right?
9=10-1 对吧
We subtracted one somewhere along the way.
这是上面某步约去1得到的
So, as ten goes to infinity,
随着10变成无穷 [c'→∞]
this is basically, this is ten minus one.
这里大概是10-1 [c'-1]
This is log of ten times e. e doesn't really matter.
这大概是 log(10e) [log(c'e)] e是无所谓的
The point is, this is logarithmic in ten.
关键是 这是对数增长的
This is linear in ten.
这是线性增长的
The thing that's linear in ten is much bigger
10的线性项远远大于
than the thing that's logarithmic in ten.
10的对数项
This is called abusive notation.
这不是正式的表示法
OK, as ten goes to infinity,
好 随着10趋于无穷
this goes to infinity, gets bigger.
这个也趋于无穷
And, there is a c out here.
这还有个c
But, for any value of c that you want,
但对于任意一个c
whatever value of c you wanted in that claim,
在断言中无论c等于多少
I can make alpha arbitrarily large
我都可以令α任意大
by changing the constant in the big O, which here was ten.
通过改变大O记号的常数 这里是10
OK, so that claim is true with high probability.
所以有高概率使断言成立
Whatever probability you want, which tells you alpha,
无论要求什么概率 也就是给出α
you set a constant in front of the log N to be this number,
只要选取它为 log n 前的常数
which grows, and you're done.
随着n的增长 就可以达到
You get the claim that is order log N heads,
从而可以得到
order log N flips with the high probability, therefore.
O(log n) 次抛硬币中有 O(log n) 个正面有高概率
Number of the steps in the search
一次搜索的步数为
is order log N with high probability.
O(log n) 是有高概率的
Really cool stuff; read the notes.
很酷吧 请阅读课后的注记
Sorry I went so fast at the end.
后面讲得有点快 不好意思哈